Finding Aid for Roy Hinman Holmes papers, 1899-1950
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Roy Hinman Holmes papers 1899-1950
Holmes, Roy Hinman, 1882-1949.
4 linear feet
851500 Aa 2
Professor of sociology at University of Michigan. Correspondence and papers relating to his professional activities; also studies of Michigan rural communities made by his students in 1933-1934.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Holmes (donor no. 844 ) and came to the library beginning in 1953.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Roy H. Holmes was born on January 3, 1882 in Sparta, Michigan. He graduated from Hillsdale College in 1911, then went on to graduate education at the University of Michigan receiving his M.A. in 1912 and eventually his PhD in 1927. Upon receipt of his masters degree, Holmes joined the Hillsdale College faculty as alumni professor of English. He remained in that post until coming to the U-M as an instructor in sociology in 1918. He served in that position until 1922 when he was made an associate professor of sociology. Holmes was a specialist in the field of rural sociology and remained at the university until his retirement in 1948. He died January 2, 1949.
As a scholar of rural sociology, Holmes is remembered for his widely used textbook Rural sociology. In the 1930s, Holmes conducted a five-year correspondence study of Michigan rural life and thought. He corresponded with individuals in most of Michigan's 83 counties for information pertaining to family farm culture, the problems of rural life, and proposed possible solutions. Although the book which was to result from this study was never published, the correspondence and summary sheets forms the core of the Holmes collection.
The Holmes collection has been arranged into five series: Correspondence, Miscellaneous, Notes and Collected Material, Student term papers, and Rural Study correspondence, 1932-1937. Except for a few explanatory comments, the contents of these series are most fully described in the container listing which follows. The Correspondence series consists of Holmes' professional correspondence with colleagues and friends. The Rural Study correspondence pertains exclusively to Holmes' inventory of the economic and social resources of the rural areas of Michigan during the 1930s. The files which are arranged alphabetically by county consist of summarizations by Holmes of the information received from his sources and copies of his responses. The file does not include, unfortunately, the originals of the letters sent to Professor Holmes.
Subjects:
Agriculture--Michigan.; Alpha Kappa Delta. Alpha Chapter (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Bellevue (Mich.); Breckenridge (Mich.); Clinton (Lenawee County, Mich.); Detroit (Mich.); Finland--Emigration and immigration.; Finnish Americans--Michigan.; Flat Rock (Mich.); Germfask (Mich.); Gladwin (Mich.); Hillsdale County (Mich.); Holly (Mich.); Immigrants--Michigan.; Ironwood (Mich.); Lake Odessa (Mich.); Lakeview (Mich.); Lenawee County (Mich.); Lincoln Consolidated School (Ypsilanti, Mich.); Livingston County (Mich.); Marlette (Mich.: Township); Michigan--Emigration and immigration.; Milford (Mich.); Monroe County (Mich.); Newaygo County (Mich.); Perronville (Mich.); Platt (Mich.); Race relations.; Rural development.; Saganing (Mich.); University High School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); University of Michigan. Dept. of Sociology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Upper Peninsula (Mich.)
- Correspondence
  - 1899, 1901-1950, undated, 19 folders (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  - Alpha Kappa Delta fraternity history (Box 1)
  - Announcements, bulletins, programs 1930-1945 of conferences and societies, with reprints of articles (Box 1)
  - Committee to Defend America by Aiding the Allies (publications and leaflets) 1930-1941 (Box 1)
  - Name lists 1940s concerning frequency of girl's names (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Sociology papers, lectures, articles and research materials 1935-1942 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Department of Sociology 1933-1945 (Box 1)
    (include minutes, reports, and proposals)
  - Undated miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Notes and collected materials
  - Introductory sociology courses 1931-1941 (Box 1)
  - Race conflict (Box 1)
  - Culture evolution, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Labor movement (Box 1)
  - Immigration, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Agriculture 1930s, 9 folders (Box 1)
- Term Papers
  - 1931 "Data concerning fifteen rural families in Marlette Township, Sanilac County" by V.G. Erwin (Box 2)
  - 1931 "Livingston County, Michigan, and its public school system" by E. Alma Sharpe (Box 2)
  - 1933 "A group analysis of Milford, Michigan" by Ruth Taylor (Box 2)
  - 1934 "The community and its effect upon surrounding country" by John M. Barnes (Flat Rock, Mich.) (Box 2)
  - 1934 "Clinton-A southern Michigan village" by Blanche H. Robison (Box 2)
  - 1935 "Rural urban health" by Alice Bringham (University High School, Ann Arbor, Mich.) (Box 2)
  - 1935 "My reaction to Gladwin" by Mildred Goldberg (Box 2)
  - 1935 "Germfask" by Leona Krueger (Box 2)
  - 1935 "A sociological survey of Platt, Michigan" by Howard Levine (Box 2)
  - 1936 "Hillsdale County" by Ray W. Barshney (Box 2)
  - 1936 "Teaching agriculture in a rural community" by A.E. Lightfoot (Holly, Mich.) (Box 2)
  - circa 1936 "Lake Odessa" by Virginia Brown York (Box 2)
  - 1937 "A statistical study of the graduates of the Lakeview High School from the years 1927-1938 inclusive" by Dorothy Gittleman (Box 2)
  - 1937 "My experience with farm life in relation to the course" by Maynard E. Hamilton (Bellevue, Mich.) (Box 2)
  - 1937 "My experiences in the rural culture" by Erwin J. Kleinert (Monroe County, Mich.) (Box 2)
  - 1937 "Experiences in a rural community" by Leonard Grant Morse (Lenawee County, Mich.) (Box 2)
  - circa 1937 "Rural community living" by L. Owen Noffsinger (Saganing, Mich.) (Box 2)
  - 1937 "An autobiography with particular reference to rural sociology" by E.E. Peterson (Breckenridge, Mich.) (Box 2)
  - 1937 "My community in terms of the family farm culture" by Floyd J. Strayer (Lenawee County, Mich.) (Box 2)
  - 1938 "Industrial influences on a community; a study of Ironwood, Michigan" by Fannie W. Johnson (Box 2)
  - 1938 "A Finnish family in an American setting" by Kathryne Makela (Ironwood, Mich.) (Box 2)
  - 1940 "A community of French becomes a community of Poles" by Joseph B. Gucky (Perronville, Mich.) (Box 2)
  - 1940 "An analysis of 191 autobiographies of eighth grade graduates of Newaygo county rural schools" (Box 2)
  - Undated "A study of rural conditions of Lincoln Consolidated School" by J. Cadaret (Box 2)
  - Undated "The farm as a social unit" by Ivor G. Penhale (Upper Peninsula, Mich.) (Box 2)
  - Undated "'Unorganized neighborliness'; the Finnish farmer" by Ivor G. Penhale (Upper Peninsula, Mich.) (Box 2)
- Rural Study Correspondence 1932-1937 (arranged by county)
  - Alcona (Box 2)
  - Allegan (Box 2)
  - Antrim (Box 2)
  - Arenac (Box 2)
  - Baraga (Box 2)
  - Barry (Box 2)
  - Benzie (Box 2)
  - Berrien (Box 2)
  - Branch (Box 2)
  - Calhoun (Box 2)
  - Chippewa (Box 2)
  - Cass (Box 2)
  - Cheboygan (Box 2)
  - Clare (Box 2)
  - Clinton (Box 2)
  - Delta (Box 2)
  - Dickinson (Box 2)
  - Eaton (Box 2)
  - Emmet (Box 2)
  - Genesee (Box 2)
  - Gladwin (Box 3)
  - Gogebic (Box 3)
  - Grand Traverse (Box 3)
  - Gratiot (Box 3)
  - Hillsdale (Box 3)
  - Houghton (Box 3)
  - Huron (Box 3)
  - Ingham (Box 3)
  - Ionia (Box 3)
  - Iosco (Box 3)
  - Iron (Box 3)
  - Isabella (Box 3)
  - Jackson (Box 3)
  - Kalamazoo (Box 3)
  - Kalkaska (Box 3)
  - Kent (Box 3)
  - Keweenaw (Box 3)
  - Lake (Box 3)
  - Lapeer (Box 3)
  - Leelanaw (Box 3)
  - Lenawee (Box 3)
  - Livingston (Box 3)
  - Luce (Box 3)
  - Mackinac (Box 3)
  - Macomb (Box 3)
  - Manistee (Box 3)
  - Marquette (Box 3)
  - Mason (Box 3)
  - Mecosta (Box 3)
  - Menominee (Box 3)
  - Midland (Box 3)
  - Missaukee (Box 3)
  - Monroe (Box 3)
  - Montcalm (Box 3)
  - Montmorency (Box 3)
  - Muskegon (Box 3)
  - Newago (Box 3)
  - Oakland (Box 4)
  - Oceana (Box 4)
  - Oceola (Box 4)
  - Ogemaw (Box 4)
  - Ontonagon (Box 4)
  - Oscoda (Box 4)
  - Otsego (Box 4)
  - Ottawa (Box 4)
  - Presque Isle (Box 4)
  - Roscommon (Box 4)
  - Saginaw (Box 4)
  - Sanilac (Box 4)
  - Schoolcraft (Box 4)
  - Shiawassee (Box 4)
  - St. Clair (Box 4)
  - St. Joseph (Box 4)
  - Tuscola (Box 4)
  - Van Buren (Box 4)
  - Washtenaw (Box 4)
  - Wayne (Box 4)
  - Wexford (Box 4)
  - Out of state counties (Box 4)
  - Reading for rural sociology course from correspondence with Michigan rural people (Box 4)
- Other materials
  - Rural Study miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Manuscript: "The Family Farm in a Changing World" (unpublished) (Box 4)